谁能告诉我发生了什么事情
Can somebody tell me what's going on?
别傻了  沃尔特  让他回去睡觉
Don't be foolish, Walter. Get him back to bed.
-把门锁上  -我还是这房子的主人
- Bar the door.  - I'm still the master of this house.
查理  起来
Richard, up.
谁在那儿
Who is there?
醒醒  汤姆斯
Wake up, Thomas.
开门
Open the gates!
混蛋
Bastards.
箭
Arrow.
灯笼
The lantern.
我看到了  你们这些小混蛋
I see you, you little bastards.
我看到你们了
I see you!
窃贼蛆
Thieving maggots.
他们偷走了我们所有的谷物种子
They've taken all our seed grain.
我们拿什么来种地
What are we going to do for planting?
祈祷吧
Pray.
你们好
Hello, there!
-给你  伙计  -谢了  罗宾
- Here you go, lad.  - Thank you, Robin.
罗宾
Robin.
弓箭手被命令集合
The archers been called to ranks.
真见鬼的会找时间  老子肚子饿坏了
Bloody typical. I'm starving.
把这些藏好了
Hide these well.
我们晚上再吃
We'll have them for supper instead.
陛下
Sire.
水准备好了  陛下
Your bath, Sire.
看在上帝的份上  洛克斯利
For the love of Christ, Loxley,
你能让他们停下吗
would you stop them doing that!
他们这样是出于对您的敬爱  陛下
They love you, Sire.
我的头  嗡嗡的吵死了
My head. It's going like the bells of hell.
就是那个吗
Is that it?
再拿下这个城堡  我们就可以荣归故里了
One more castle to sack, then we're home to England.
查理国王万岁
Hail King Richard!
放箭
Release!
推
Push!
弓箭手
Hey, archer!
别丢了小命
Stay alive!
晚上见
I'll see you tonight.
这次别忘了带钱  小伙子
Don't forget your money this time, little man.
我很乐于把它从你手上赢过来
It will be my pleasure to take it off you.
推
Push!
冲上去
Move up!
掩护国王  掩护国王
Cover the King! Cover the King!
盾牌准备
Barricades prepare!
让我们干掉这些法国佬
Let us put these French to bed!
翻起盾牌
Raise the barricades!
吉米
Jimmy.
沉着小心  别浪费机会
Calm and careful. Make it count.
出击
Go!
救命啊
Help!
掩护
Cover!
现在跳
Now.
跑
Go!
回撤
Move back!
血染法国
Blood for France!
出击
Go!
马上就要被射成刺猬了
It'll make a fine pin cushion!
菲利普国王去死吧
King Philip's arse!
狮心王所向披靡
Look what they do for the Lion Heart!
推
Push!
这会烧整个晚上  伙计们   别让他们给扑灭了
That'll burn all night, lads.  Don't let them put it out.
我们冲锋陷阵  最后论功赏的却是这些
These pricks will smash through in the morning,
第二天早上才轻轻松松冲进去的混球
take all the credit.
干的好  小吉米
Well done, Jimmy boy.
约翰...
John...
女王陛下
Your Majesty.
英国公主因为一个法国小妞
An English Princess shut out of her husband's bedchamber
被其丈夫拒之门外
by a piece of French pastry!
你不觉得羞愧吗
Aren't you ashamed?
该羞愧的是他
The shame is surely his.
那就进去告诉他
Then go in and tell him.
在他门前像孩子一样哭泣一点都不管用
Mewling at his keyhole is neither one thing nor the other.
约翰
John.
上帝  怎么回事...
Oh, God! What in heaven...
小姐  抱歉
Mademoiselle, you will excuse me.
我的儿子需要我的建议
My son has need of my advice.
不  我不需要  不信你问她
No, I don't. Ask her.
母后  拜托  你不觉得这不合适吗
Mother, please, have you no decency?
我刚好在干
I happen to be in a condition
任何母亲都不应该看的事情
that no mother should see her son in.
我也不想  但那是我母后
- Yes, I know, but it's my mother.
够了
- That's enough.
再想想
On second thoughts,
我觉得你最好还是听我要说的话
I think it better that  you do hear what I have to say.
但我不想让你出现在我的眼前
Though I will not have you in my presence.
母后
Mother.
我出现在这里的目的是从这不适当的娱乐中
The purpose of my being in this room is to save the realm
拯救这个王国
from the consequences of this unsuitable amusement.
她叔叔就是那见鬼的法国国王
Her uncle is the bloody King of France.
-我叔叔是...  -没你说话的份
- My uncle is... - Get down.
她叔叔想让她回去
Her uncle wants her back.
菲利普正需要一个
Philip wants an excuse
出兵越过海峡的借口
to cross the channel with an army.
你却给了他那个理由
And you have given him that excuse.
回到你法定妻子的身边  拯救英格兰
Take up your lawful wife and save England.
我的法定妻子木得像块砖
My lawful wife is as barren as a brick.
你真的想让我有那样的妻子吗
Is that truly the wife you want for me?
您以八个子女让您的丈夫荣耀
You, who honoured your husband with eight children
即使现在  当其他的子女都已逝去
so that even now when death has taken the rest
您还有一个国王和一个叫您母后的傀儡
You have a King and the runt of the litter to call you "mother".
我宁愿你找侍女生私生子
Better the bastard of a servant girl
也好过和嫉妒英格兰的敌人的侄女上床
than bed the niece of England's jealous enemy.
我要和她上床并且娶她  母后
Or bed her and wed her, mother.
我已经让教皇的人准备好废黜事宜了
I've asked the Pope's men to arrange an annulment.
你认为教皇
And do you think the Pope
相比法国国王会更喜欢英国傀儡吗
will favour England's royal runt over the King of France?
他也许就是这样认为的  因为我是亚奎丹的埃莉诺的儿子
He might see his way for the son of Eleanor of Aquitaine.
同时也是英格兰未来的国王
And for the future King of England.
狮心王查理已经至少四十了  甚至更老
Richard the Lion Heart is 40-years-old, if not more.
没有子嗣
And no babies.
我是未来的皇后
I am a queen in the maKing.
对  没错
Yes. Yes.
看到了吗
You see?
她是我的埃莉诺
She is my Eleanor.
现在明白了吗  这游戏不靠运气
Now, you do understand, this game is not about luck.
靠的是记忆力和手法
It's about the science of memory and a quick hand.
谁想带点鲜肉回家
Who'd like to take a bit of fresh meat home?
我们今早还捕了一只野鸡
Caught this morning. We have a pheasant.
三选一  右边  左边  还是中间
Three choices. Right, left or middle?
中间
Middle.
"中间"  他说选中间
"The middle," he says. The middle.
抱歉那些洋葱归我了  伙计  你输了
I'm sorry about those onions, young man. You lose.
罗宾  扔过来  我这儿正好要洋葱调味
Robin! Over here, they're needed for the pot.
绝对新鲜
Feisty one!
还有什么  还有什么
Aye, what else we got, what else we got?
火会完成它的使命
The fire will do its work.
我们天一亮就进攻
We break through at first light.
不出意外  我们三天之后就可以到家了
With a fair wind, we can be home in three days.
你要回诺丁汉吗
You return to Nottingham?
我有妻子在那儿等着我
I have a wife who waits for me.
我有个老不死的母后
I have a mother that won't die
还有个巴不得我早死的弟弟
and a brother who wishes me dead.
我回去的第一件事就是把他们关起来
First thing I'm going to do is lock them up.
你的人民会很高兴看到你归来
Your people will rejoice to see you return home.
那也是我希望保持的现象
And that is a condition I would like to keep them in.
和以前一样被历史铭记
To be remembered as I was.
我的军队更了解
My army knows better.
狮心是污秽的
Lion Heart is mangy.
军队里的每个人都敬仰您  陛下
Every man in that army idolises you, your Majesty.
别拍我马屁
Don't mollycoddle me.
我知道和国王做朋友有多难
I understand how difficult it must be to be friend a King.
好了  洛克斯利  让我们找点乐子  开怀畅饮一下
Come on, Loxley. Let us find some ruffians, drink and laugh.
看看能不能找到一个诚实的人
Let us see if we can find an honest man.
好
Yes.
就这样
Let's do that.
伙计  事实是   这游戏不靠运气
Well, that's the thing, little man. This is not a game of luck.
靠的是记忆力和手法
It's about the science of memory and a quick hand.
我有火眼金睛   我会牢牢盯着你的
I've got a quick eye. I'll be watching you.
三选一
Three choices.
右边  左边  还是中间
Right, left, or middle.
我想我要选第四个
I think I'll take a fourth choice.
第四个吗
A fourth?
我看了你很久了  朗斯特莱德
I've been watching you for a while now, Longstride.
这里根本没有豌豆
There is no pea.
这是个骗人的把戏
This game is a trick!
你换碗的时候
You take out the pea
就把豌豆拿出去了
when you're doing your slidings and your turnings.
我识破你的伎俩了
I got you.
别再碰它
Don't touch it again.
我来
I'll do it!
你输了
You lose.
你其实干得挺不错的
You're doing better than you think.
过这儿来  罗宾
Get in there, Robin.
跪下  你们这些无知的混蛋
Kneel, you ignorant bastards!
在国王面前跪下
Kneel before the King!
你们都退回去  快
All of you, move back, now.
不  不  洛克斯利   这些士兵只是在玩儿
No, no, Loxley. These men are soldiers at play.
怪罪他们我就成了罪人了
Sinners after mine own heart.
你们谁先挑起的
Which one of you started the fight?
是我  陛下
I did, Sire.
我挥的第一拳
I threw the first punch.
诚实的人
Ah, honest man.
你跟谁打
And who're you fighting?
他在跟我打  陛下
He was fighting me, your Majesty.
我认为他是个骗子
I thought him to be a lesser man.
但他证明了他不是
He was showing me different.
一个向对手表示尊敬的敌人
An enemy that shows his respect.
你们平身
Stand up, the pair of you.
不是你们
Not you.
勇敢  诚实
Brave and honest.
但你会足够诚实到告诉一个国王
Are you honest enough to tell a King
他不愿意听的事情吗
something that he does not want to hear?
你对我的东征有何看法
What is your opinion on my crusade?
神会喜欢我的献祭吗
Will god be pleased with my sacrifice?
不  他不会
No, he won't.
为什么这么说
Why do you say that?
阿卡里的大屠杀  陛下
The massacre at Acre, Sire.
大声点
Speak up!
当您命令我们把两千五百穆斯林
When you had us herd 2,500 Muslim
男女和儿童赶到一起
men, women, and children together,
在我脚边  手被绑着的那位女士
the young woman at my feet, with her hands bound,
抬头看着我
she looked up at me.
她眼神里没有恐惧  没有怒气
There wasn't fear in her eyes. There wasn't anger.
只有怜悯
There was only pity.
因为她知道当您下令
For she knew that when you gave the order
我们砍下他们的头颅那刻起
and our blades would descend upon their heads,
我们就失去了神的护佑
that, in that moment, we would be godless.
我们所有人
All of us.
都会失去神的护佑
Godless.
诚实
Honest,
勇敢
brave
这就是英格兰子民
There is your Englishman.
就在这儿
Right there.
-干的好  罗宾  -你告诉他了
- Well done, Robin.  - You showed him.
最坏就是挨鞭刑了
The whipping will be the worst of it.
烙铁  那才是最坏的
The branding iron, that will be the worst.
除非他们用绞刑
Unless they hang us.
不  这才是最坏的
No. No, this will be the worst of it.
这也代表着结束
And this will be the end of it.
一旦从这儿逃出来  我立马走人
As soon as I get out of here, I'm gone.
我不欠上帝或者这里的任何其他人哪怕是一分一秒的服役
I don't owe God or any other man here one more minute of service.
我们是同一个妈喂大的
We go all the way back to the same breast.
奶妈吗
Wet nurse.
是的
Indeed.
我们一直以来都很亲密
We've been close ever since.
很好
Good.
因为英格兰在你朋友约翰的统治下
Because England, under your friend John,
是个失去了战斗灵魂的国度
is a country with no fighting spirit.
我用一队厨子就能轻取伦敦
I can take London with an army of cooks.
但是查理正在归乡途中
But Richard is on his way home.
在他的统治下  英格兰会山河日下
And under Richard,  England is a different animal altogether.
查理班师回朝会经过布罗塞利昂德森林
Richard will return home through the forest of Broceliande.
我们知道准确的地点
We know the exact place.
他总是走在军队的前面
He always travels ahead of his army
只有一些被信赖的骑士跟着他
with only a few trusted knights around him.
如果查理死了
With Richard dead,
你很容易就可以策反贵族  抵抗约翰的统治
it will be easy for you to turn the country against John.
没有比这更好的入侵机会了
There'll never be a better moment to invade.
但百足之虫  死而不僵
Even dying animals can be obstinate.
杀了狮心王  你会被重赏
Kill the Lion Heart and you will be richly rewarded.
撞
Heave!
为了英格兰
For England!
我需要一名医生
I need a physician here!
医生  快点
A physician! Quickly!
掩护我们  掩护我们  快
Give us cover! Give us cover, now!
掩护国王
Cover him!
Cover the King.
医生
Physician!
怎么了  洛克斯利  你不舒服吗
Why, Loxley? Are you not feeling well?
医生
Physician!
酒
Wine.
怎么了
What's this?
-国王死了  -死了
- The King is dead!  - Dead?
死了
Dead.
那么吉米  把钉子敲出去
All right, then, Jimmy. Knock the pegs out.
现在我们自己掌控命运
We make our own fate from now on!
我跟你一块
I'll come with you.
不  你不行  我们不收流浪狗
No, you're not. We don't take strays.
人越多越好
The more the merrier.
路上很危险  他可能会有用
The road will be dangerous. He might be useful.
我们去哪
Where we going?
我们要赶在三千绝望的士兵之前
To the coast and to a boat
到达岸边  找到船只
before 3,000 desperate soldiers get there
渡过海峡的价格很快会上涨一百倍
and the price for a channel crossing goes up a hundredfold.
我们的军饷怎么办
What about our wages?
如果你觉得他活着的时候就已经很难获得军饷
If you thought it was hard getting wages while he was alive,
试试去让死去的国王付你钱
try getting paid by a dead King.
好了  伙计们  迅速收拾行李
All right, boys, collect your gear as quick as you can.
我喜欢这个新教堂
I like the new church.
马里昂夫人
Lady Marion.
你没来送行的话
I would have been sorry
我会很遗憾的  谢谢
to leave without your farewell. Thank you.
很乐意为您践行  坦克雷德神父
I'm glad to speed you on your way, Father Tancred,
但我来是为了找我们的新牧师
but it was to seek out our new shepherd.
您最近都没来参加我的周日礼拜和传教
You have lately been missed at Sunday worship and my sermons.
当我祈祷奇迹的时候  我喜欢安静的教堂  神父
I like a quiet church, Father, when I pray for a miracle.
您的受众是妇女  儿童和老人
Your new flock is women, children and old folk.
我们的男人在浴血奋战  或受伤归来
Our men have gone to war or returned broken.
他们的孤儿在绿林中撒野
Their orphans run wild in the greenwood.
我们土地已经可以播种了  但我们没有种子
Our fields are ready for planting but we've no seed corn.
而教堂的粮仓谷物丰硕
And the church barn is full of grain.
你不会是在期待教堂把它的谷物
Surely, you do not expect the church
种在你们的土地上吧
to let its corn be used to plant your fields?
这些粮食是约克的
That grain is bound for York.
我是修道士塔克
I am Friar Tuck.
坦克雷德神父被升迁到约克
Father Tancred is elevated to York
我想他到那儿会提醒主教
where I know he will remind the bishop
诺丁汉的人民...
that the people of Nottingham...
主教不需要提醒诺丁汉的人民
The bishop does not need reminding that the people of Nottingham
恶有恶报  忏悔种孽
should reap what they sow and repent of their sins.
我祈祷的奇迹是
The miracle I pray for is that
主教展现一些基督教的仁慈
the bishop show some christian charity.
我说过  神父  我喜欢在安静的教堂祈祷
As I said, Father, I like a quiet church when I pray.
佩珀哈罗的洛克斯利家族会找你麻烦的
You will have trouble from the Loxleys of Peper Harow.
塔克  你养蜂吗
You keep bees, Tuck?
我养蜂  蜂为我服务
I keep them and they keep me.
停下
Stop!
有埋伏
Ambush!
你是个骑士吗
You're a knight?
查理国王在哪里
Where is King Richard?
我的天啊
Oh, God.
国王在哪儿
Where is the King?
-死了  -他死了
- Dead. - Dead?
真的吗
Really?
如果国王已死  你们这是前往何处
If the King's dead, where are you going?
护送王冠
Deliver the crown.
查理的王冠
Richard's crown.
我们怎么去暗杀一个死掉的国王
How do we assassinate a King who's already dead?
把王冠追回来  把马杀死
Bring back the crown! Kill the horse!
你是英国人
You are English.
这么说也行
When it suits me.
你是谁
Who are you?
罗伯特・洛克斯利
Robert Loxley.
那是国王的马
That's the King's horse.
吉米  闪开
Jimmy! Move!
吉米
Jimmy!
罗宾  他们是法国人
Robin, they're French.
一定是个埋伏
Ambush.
冲啊
Go.
约翰  什么情况
John.
不知道
Don't know.
他死了
He's dead.
救命
Help.
请把剑给我
My sword.
这剑对我意义重大
Its value to me is great.
原本是我父亲的剑
It belonged to my father,
他是诺丁汉的
Sir Walter Loxley
沃尔特・洛克斯利爵士
of Nottingham.
你听说过吗
Do you know it?
是的  我听说过诺丁汉
Aye, I've heard of Nottingham.
感谢老天
Then the fate...
感谢上苍眷顾
The fates have smiled on me.
请你务必将剑交到我父亲手中
You must take the sword to my father.
这会让我安息
It will bring me peace.
我当年盛怒之下  未经他允许带离此剑
I took it in anger and without his consent.
你一定懂得
You must understand the bond of love
这种父子间的羁绊
between a father and his son.
我父亲在我六岁时
My father abandoned me to the world of men
就把我遗弃了
when I was six years old.
我对父子之情不甚了解
I know little of the love between father and son.
我请求你
I beg you.
朗斯特莱德
Longstride,
答应我
say you will.
我答应你
I will.
你以血起誓了  罗宾
It's a pact sworn in blood, Robin.
埃伦  只不过是划伤罢了  仅此而已
It's a scratch, Allan, and that's all it is.
罗宾
Robin!
洛克斯利原本要去海边和舰队会和
Loxley was making for the coast to meet the ship.
王冠可以让我们顺利回家
That crown could be our passage home.
罗宾  我们只是普通的弓箭手
We're common archers, Robin.
如果带着王冠出现在国王的船上
If we arrive at the King's ship with his crown,
我们会被告谋杀
we'll be accused of murder.
你怎么肯定
How do you know
看到的那些骑士
that the knights you see walking
就一定是真的骑士呢
about are actually knights at all?
区分骑士和平民的唯一标志
There is no difference between a knight
就是着装
and any other man aside from what he wears.
我们乔装打扮即可
All we need is about us.
找来甲胄  头盔  剑
Armour, helmets, swords,
我们就可以伪装成骑宝马  带金子上路的
and we make England wealthy men
英格兰富人
with horses and gold.
命运终于垂青我们了
Fate has smiled upon us at last.
而我  绝不会放弃这大好良机
And I, for one, shall not turn my back on her.
把王冠摘下来  威尔
Take that crown off your head, Will,
装满金银财宝更有用些
And fill it to the brim.
主啊  我们将此人的灵魂交给您保管
We commit the soul of this boy to your keeping, Lord.
当他到达永生之门时  我们请求
We would ask, when he arrives at the gates of eternity,
您能让他得以永生
if you could let him in.
歌利亚把地犁得很好  但种什么呢
Goliath's got the soil turning nicely. But for what?
荨麻吗
- Nettles?
荨麻汤和蒲公英沙拉
- Nettle soup and dandelion salad,
我们至少可以活命
that'll keep us alive.
歌利亚  这边来
Come, Goliath. this way.
直到奇迹出现
Until we get a miracle.
这边
This way.
马里昂  郡督来了
Marion, Sheriff.
马里昂  我在佩珀哈罗始终没有得到
Marion, I've been at Peper Harow, waiting in vain
沃尔特爵士的接见
for Sir Walter to receive me.
烦请转告  我有别的事忙
Kindly tell him I have better things to do
不能在府上久候
than haunt his threshold.
舍伍德盗贼横行的时候  你倒是悠哉悠哉
That you have, while robbers are roaming free in Sherwood.
那是郡督的职责  你怎么不操心
That's Sheriff's business. Why don't you look to it?
告诉那个老家伙  下次我会破门而入
Tell the old fool that next time, I'll break his door down.
而且如果他太骄傲而不付...
And if he's too proud to pay...
不  他不是太骄傲
No, no, no, no. He's not too proud.
他是太穷了
He's too poor.
以查理国王之名  你们搜刮民脂
In the name of King Richard, you have stripped our wealth
只顾出外征战
to pay for foreign adventures.
而在地方上还有教堂  以仁慈的上帝之名
Whilst at home, the church, in the name of the merciful god,
毫不留情地掠夺
has reaped, without mercy,
我们赖以糊口的存粮
the largest share of what we had set aside to feed ourselves.
我已经无从分辨  郡督和主教之间
Between a Sheriff and a Bishop, I wouldn't care to judge
到底谁压榨老实的英国人更多
who's the greater curse on honest English folk.
马里昂
Marion,
当你有办法能让我成为你的保护者的时候
Why,why do you make an enemy of me
为什么还要选择与我为敌
when you have the means to make me your protector?
你指什么办法
What means?
如果你现在就滚
If you leave now,
你还能活得长久些  等我丈夫回来时
I will lengthen your life by not telling my husband
我不会把你来骚扰的事告诉他
of your visit when he returns home.
你丈夫  都十年没回来了
Your husband? After 10 years?
如果他还没死
If he's not dead,
那一定是在北非海岸的温柔乡  乐不思蜀了
He's rutting his way through the brothels of the Barbary Coast.
只有你这种下流胚才会这样
So speaks a man of experience.
好好想想吧  马里昂
Well, think on it, Marion.
沃尔特爵士后继无人
Sir Walter is dying without an heir.
他死后佩珀哈罗将归由国王所有
Peper Harow will fall to the crown,
到时你就睡大街吧
and you will be living in the hedgerow.
你会后悔没来从我的
You'll be glad to come to me then.
船长  看那里
Captain, there.
先生  应是12名骑士和国王一同登船
Sir, we were told to expect 12 riders and the King.
我们爱戴的国君已经去世
Our beloved King is dead.
吾王永恒
Long live the King.
请问阁下是
And you are, Sir?
诺丁汉罗伯特・洛克斯利爵士  你是
Sir Robert Loxley of Nottingham. And you?
我是国王侍从
I'm the King's equerry, Sir.
先生们  上船吧
Come aboard, gentlemen, before
马上要涨潮了
the tide floats her. It's coming in fast.
划船啊  壮士们  在赶路  壮士们
And it's row, me bully boys we're in a hurry, boys.
长路漫漫
We got a long way to go
我们载歌载舞  告别法国
where we'll sing and we'll dance and bid farewell to France.
划船啊  壮士们  划船啊
And row, me bully boys, row.
划船啊  壮士们  在赶路  壮士们
And it's row, me bully boys we're in a hurry boys.
长路漫漫
We got a long way to go.
我们载歌载舞  告别法国
We'll sing and we'll dance and bid farewell to France.
划船啊  勇士们  划船啊
And row, me bully boys, row.
早上有什么计划
So what's the plan in the morning?
船到伦敦前会在格雷夫森德停靠
The boat stops at Gravesend on the way to London.
我们会将归还王冠的荣誉让给他们
We'll leave the honour of returning the crown to them,
然后我们就离开
and we'll be gone.
去哪里
Where?
去北方
North.
我喜欢
Well, that suits me.
划船啊  壮士们  划船啊
Row, me bully boys, row.
但如今我们归航  快看紧家里的姑娘们
But now we're returning so lock up your daughters.
我们载歌载舞  告别法国
We'll sing and we'll dance and bid farewell to France.
划船啊  壮士们  划船啊
And it's row, me bully boys, row.
罗伯特爵士  做好准备  我们二十分钟后靠岸
Make ready, Sir Robert. We dock in 20 minutes.
到格雷夫森德了吗
Gravesend?
不  大人  在伦敦塔  王宫处靠岸
No, my Lord. The palace docks, Tower of London.
威尔
Will.
约翰  埃伦
John. Allan.
-我们到哪里了  -伦敦
- Where are we? - London.
我的老天
Holy Christ!
咱们10分钟后靠岸
We dock in 10 minutes.
这件事一了结  我们就跑路
When this is done, be ready to ride.
如果王太后或者别的什么皇亲国戚
What if... what if Loxley is known
认得洛克斯利  被识破了怎么办
to the King's mother or brother or any of them?
那我们就亡命天涯
Then we'll be riding for our lives.
耶稣  圣母  圣父  圣人彼得  保罗和玛丽
Jesus, Mary and Joseph.
我就知道会出事
I knew it! I knew it!
早安  大人
Good morning, my Lord.
值此悲伤之际  我想嘱咐您几句
Some words of advice on this tragic occasion.
接下来要做的事不能出差错
You appreciate everything must be done correctly,
您要将王冠呈给埃莉诺王太后
So you will present the crown to Lady Eleanor.
右膝下跪
You will go down on the right knee.
告知国王死讯时  不要直视她的眼睛
Do not look in her eyes when you tell her the King is no more.
别人没起身时要一直跪着  你听明白了吗
And do not rise until all others rise. Do you understand?
明白
Yes.
爱格妮思
Agnes.
拿我的蓝底金线裙来
My blue and gold brocade.
是  王太后
Yes, my Lady.
给王太后让路
Part for the Queen.
停
Cease.
怎么回事  发生什么事情
What's this? What's happening?
查理从法国回来了
King Richard returns from France, my lord.
洛克斯利骗了我们吗
Did Loxley deceive us?
跪下
Kneel.
吾儿万岁
Long life, my son.
平身
Rise now.
先王已逝
A King is dead.
吾王万岁
Long live the King.
Long live the King!
-吾王万岁  -吾王万岁
- Long live the King! - Long live the King!
平身
Rise.
你是...
You...
我不认识你
I don't know you.
陛下  我是诺丁汉罗伯特・洛克斯利爵士
Robert Loxley, Sire, of Nottingham.
那欢迎来到王宫
Welcome then.
我哥哥是怎么死的
And how did my brother die?
回陛下  先王战死沙场  死得其所
In battle, your Majesty, as was his way.
死得其所
As was his way.
你将消息带回国都
You deserve a reward...
去备马
Let's get the horses.
值得嘉奖
...for bringing home the news.
跪下
Kneel.
你是从诺丁汉来的吗
Did you say you were from Nottingham?
是
Yes.
你的父亲  沃尔特爵士
Your father, Sir Walter,
欠王室税款
Owes tax to the crown.
欠我钱
My crown.
告诉他  治理国家  开销惊人
Tell him it's bloody expensive running a country
为国纳税  人人有责
and everyone's got to pay their way.
这戒指就当是你偿还的第一笔欠款吧
We'll start with this.
给国王让路
Make way for the King!
让开
Make way!
陛下
Your Majesty.
给国王让路
Make way for the King!
-让开  -戈弗雷
- Make way! - Godfrey.
戈弗雷  我的老友  见到你真好
Godfrey, my friend. It's so good to see you.
-旅行如何  -很好  陛下
- How were your travels? - Good, Sire.
你的脸怎么弄伤了
What happened to your face?
狩猎意外  无须挂怀
A hunting accident. It's nothing.
-有些狰狞  -陛下
- Frightening. - Your Majesty.
就说是决斗留下的  姑娘们会对你更痴迷的
Call it a duelling scar.
向您阅女无数而致意  陛下
I bow to your knowledge of the ladies, Sire.
请起吧
You can get up now.
罗伯特爵士
Sir Robert.
你也许听说过我
You will know of me, perhaps.
我是威廉姆・马歇尔
I'm William Marshal.
我年轻时和你父亲情同手足
Your father and I were young men together.
告诉他我很快会去看他
Tell him I'm coming to visit him soon,
在春天的第一个夜晚
on Spring's first black night.
我可能会需要他帮忙
I may have need of him.
好的  我会转告他
I will. I'll tell him.
不管他是谁  有什么背景  他知道的太多了
Whoever he is and whatever he is,
除掉他
Get rid of him.
大家跟上
Come on, let's follow.
交出你手里的东西
Forfeit what you got.
粮食  钱财  衣服
Victuals, coin, clothing
不然你就没命了
...or your life.
汤姆斯・库珀
Thomas Cooper.
是你吗
Is that you?
汤姆斯  你病了吗
Are you sick, Thomas?
我们都病了
We're all sick.
-其他人在哪儿  -别告诉她
- Where are the rest of you? - Don't... don't tell her.
洛普会生气的
Loop will be angry.
不  生气的是你妈妈
No, it's your mother who's going to be angry.
要么你们出来跟我走  要么我过去
Now, either you come with me, or I come with you.
你们选吧
You choose.
快说  他们在哪儿
Well, come on then. Where are they?
告诉我
Answer me.
4个人  5匹马  其中一匹是灰白色的
Four men, five horses, one grey.
你见过他们吗
- Have you seen them?
往那边走了
- That way.
现今布道之王
The living King of sermons
从邪恶中被释放
was delivered from his evil
但他无法留下遗言
but he couldn't talk his last
因为上帝扼住他的喉咙
because God took out his throat.
上帝用弩扼住他的喉咙
God's crossbow took out his throat.
老天  你就不能唱点喜庆的歌啊
By Christ! Can you not sing a happy tune?
唱一曲关于冒险  勇敢和勇气的踢踏舞曲
Sing a foot-stomper about adventure and daring and courage.
不  唱首关于女人的歌
No. Sing something about a woman.
身材丰满的女人
A large woman.
美妙军营  我爱你爱到心里
Fancy army, darling I loves you all to bits.
我会爬进你的卧室  埋在你双峰下
I'll climb up to your chamber and under your mountainous...
好了  我把钱分好了
Right. I'm done. The money's divided.
我们也该分道扬镳了
And so should we be.
你要去哪里
Where will you go?
这笔钱财我拿得不心安
I think something is owed for this good fortune,
我要设法补偿
...and I mean to pay it back.
怎么补偿
How so?
剑上的铭文  在我脑中挥之不去
The inscription on the sword, it taunts my memory.
或许只是我的想象  我不知道
Maybe it's just my imagination, I don't know.
但我打算将剑带回它的主人身边
But I intend to take that sword back to its owner
完成他儿子临死前的请求
...and fulfil the request of his dying son.
你是不是疯了
Are you mad?
罗宾  你刚说过我们身处险境
You just said we were in danger, Robin.
你现在却决定折回  以身犯险吗
Now you choose to step back in to harm's way?
他们一定会在那里设下陷阱等你
They're bound to go there and find you.
我们不能出尔反尔  这会招来厄运
We can't repay our good luck with bad grace. It invites darkness.
-我和你一起去  -还有我  罗宾
- I'm going with you. - And I, Robin.
-没错  -不行
- Yes. - No.
今晚是我们最后一次相聚
Tonight is our last in company.
明天  我们分道扬镳
Tomorrow, we go our separate ways.
拿好自己那份钱  吃饭睡觉
Pack up your share. We eat and sleep.
威尔  你值第一轮班
Will, you're on first watch.
威尔
Will.
小心点
Watch your step!
有一个跑了
One of them got away.
混蛋  他们偷了我的钱
Bastards! They've stolen my fortune.
查理的军队在回家的路上
Richard's army is coming home.
维持军队需要经费
It costs money to keep it together.
马歇尔  经费一向由你负责
Marshal, you speak for the money.
是的  陛下
I do, Sire.
但遣散军队比维持花费更大
But to disband the army could cost more than to keep it.
查理国王的征伐耗资巨大  但战争获利却
King Richard's campaigns were costly.
马歇尔  那和我有什么关系
What is that to me, Marshal?
我哥哥的烂摊子我才不管
My brother's troubles are over!
都结束了
They're over!
你们都退下
Clear the room.
那...只能增加税收了
So... taxation.
增加税收
Taxation?
无止尽的挤奶只会让奶牛
Milking a dry udder gets you nothing but
把你从挤奶凳上踢下来
kicked off the milking stool.
母后  少用你那小农思想折磨我
Mother, spare me your farmyard memories.
你没当过农民  我也搞不懂他们
You have none, and I don't understand them.
现在形势不稳定
These are difficult times.
但我们可以争取时间
We can buy time.
我可以派特使去贷款
I can send envoys to secure loans.
从西西里到诺曼底
There are money chests from Sicily to
遍布财富只要你知道在哪
Normandy if you know where to look.
卑躬屈膝的去找高利贷吗
Cap-in-hand to moneylenders?
你的主人可是国王
Your master's a King.
国内所有人欠国家的钱
The crown is owed money at home.
北方贵族借口贫穷不愿交税
The northern Barons plead poverty,
不过喜欢装穷的总是那些富人
but that's always been the song of rich men.
那么下一步怎么做
So, what's to be done?
给我点时间陛下  我要带着骑兵北征
Give me leave, Sire, to go north with a company of mounted men.
我会让那些商人和地主乖乖交钱
I'll have the merchants and landowners fill your coffers.
不然就送他们进坟墓
Or their coffins.
你这是让英格兰人自相残杀
Englishmen killing Englishmen.
忠于国王的人都无所畏惧
No man loyal to the crown has anything to fear.
忠诚也同时意味着你要向国家缴税
And loyalty means paying your share in the defence of the realm.
说的好
That's well said.
马歇尔  你觉得呢
Hmm? Don't you think, Marshal?
母后
Mother?
查理以身作则博取忠诚而不是威逼恐吓
Richard commanded loyalty not by threats but by example.
母后  你那圣子是个低能儿
Mother, your sainted son was an imbecile.
从这儿到耶路撒冷来来回回
And you supported his every folly
他每次犯蠢你都支持他
from here to Jerusalem and back.
是的  你崇拜他
Yes, you worshipped him.
当战士们丢掉了父辈打拼来的土地时
When the warrior lost territories hard won by his father.
你亲吻他的照片
You kissed his picture.
英格兰甚至不得不付四年的税款
While England had to pay four years' revenue
赎回被敌军俘虏的他
to ransom him when he was captured.
你跟所有人一样都该受到谴责
You are just as much to blame as anyone,
因为你们毁了我的遗产
for the wreckage which is my inheritance.
她刚才比我更丢脸
I broke her skin more than she did mine.
大法官
Chancellor.
马歇尔
Marshal,
你先后忠诚地服侍了我的父亲和我哥哥
you served my brother faithfully and my father before him.
我觉得你待在我家族身边的时间已经够长了
I think you've spent enough time with my family.
毋须质疑  你一定也想享受下天伦之乐吧
And, no doubt, would like to spend more with your own.
所以  我很遗憾地接受你的请辞
Therefore, and with regret,
你可以离开办公室
I accept your resignation of
放下一切国家事务了
all your offices and matters of state.
交出戒指吧
The ring.
尊敬的陛下
Your Majesty.
戈弗雷  好好斟酌下
Choose carefully, Godfrey, the spot
你想把匕首往哪儿捅
where you would place your dagger.
因为我也会仔细琢磨这个问题的
For I will choose carefully, as well.
打开城门
Open the gates!
诺丁汉
Nottingham.
罗宾  这些就是你的子民吗
Is this your people, Robin?
不知道  也许吧
I don't know. Might be.
这些中庸的英格兰人看起来不怎么富有
They don't look much, these middle Englanders.
但是他们把你们养得白白胖胖的
Well, they've been keeping your lot in place
不是吗
easy enough, haven't they?
我听说你们威尔士小伙子就吃韭菜过活
I hear that you welsh boys, you live on leeks.
跟绵羊一个爱好
You co-habit with sheep.
去你的苏格兰蠢驴
Bloody scottish mule.
你不想惊动蜂窝吧
You wouldn't want to annoy a bee hive with your noise, would you?
到时候你们的剑可是毫无用处呢  先生们
Your swords would be no good then, gentlemen.
你是镇上的养蜂人吗
You're the town beekeeper?
不  神保佑你  我是修道士塔克
Bless you, no. I'm the Friar. Tuck's the name.
塔克修道士
Well, Friar Tuck,
能告诉我  沃尔特・洛克斯利爵士住在哪儿吗
can you tell me
他应该在佩珀哈罗
If he's not up at Peper Harow...
你要去多久
How long will your business take?
注意安全
Stay safe.
上帝与你们同在
God be with you all.
就这样吗
That's it?
十年相处就这样结束吗
After 10 years?
善良的修道士  这附近哪儿有能让人
Good Friar, where can a man get, well,
一醉方休的地方
moderately insensible on a drink around here?
埃伦  他是个教士  对不起修道士
Allan, he's a man of the cloth. I'm sorry, Friar.
你有钱吗
- Have you coin?
我有
- I have coin.
两块
Two pieces.
每个人两块
Each.
尝过我们这里的蜜糖酒吗
Have you tried the honey liquor we call Mead?
跟我来
Come with me.
蜜糖酒能让人有头顶光环的感觉
Gives a man a halo, does Mead.
姑娘
Girl.
喊我姑娘
Girl?
你不是瞎了就是来讨钱的
Either you're going blind or you're looking for charity.
你是这房子的主人吗
Are you the keeper of this house?
某种意义上来说  是的
In a manner of speaking, yes.
我想见沃尔特・洛克斯利爵士
I wish to see Sir Walter Loxley.
你是
And you are?
罗宾・朗斯特莱德
Robin Longstride.
光是罗宾・朗斯特莱德  不用加爵士吗
Plain Robin Longstride? No Sir?
不用  女士  不用加
No, ma'am. No Sir.
你是来收税的吗
Are you here about the tax?
不  我是来把剑带给他的  他儿子牺牲了
No, I'm here to bring him his sword. His son's dead.
跟我来
This way.
他会照看你的马
He'll take your horse.
马里昂
Marion!
玛吉  她去哪儿了
Maggie, where is she?
夫人  沃尔特爵士在找你
Ma'am, Sir Walter calls for you.
我知道  玛格利特  我听到了
I know, Margaret. I can hear him.
告诉他来客人了
Tell him we have a guest.
我是马里昂・洛克斯利  罗伯特的妻子
I'm Marion Loxley. Robert's wife.
对不起亲爱的夫人  如果我知道就不会说了
My lady, I owe you an apology. If I'd have known...
坏消息只会是坏消息  早点晚点都一样
Bad news is bad news no matter how it comes.
我反倒该谢谢你
Indeed, I owe you thanks for taking the time
亲自把剑送来了
to deliver it here yourself.
你曾经和我丈夫一起战斗吗
Did you fight alongside my husband?
是的
Yes.
他的最后时刻得体吗
Did he die well?
他中埋伏了  夫人
In an ambush, ma'am.
他被选去护送查理的皇冠回国
He was the man chosen to bring home Richard's crown.
马里昂  谁来了
Marion, who is here?
是个过路人  沃尔特
A traveller, Walter.
这消息会让他绝望的
This news will go very hard on him.
带他进来
Bring him in.
知道了  知道了
Yes, yes.
告诉他罗伯特在圣地就快回来了
Tell him Robert is in the Holy Land,
托你来报平安的
sends his love and will return soon.
马里昂  我们的旅者一定渴了
Marion, our traveller will be thirsty.
旅者总是渴的  难道不是吗
Travellers are always thirsty. Is that not so?
先生你叫什么名字
Your name, Sir?
朗斯特莱德  罗宾・朗斯特莱德
Longstride. Robin longstride.
你在开我玩笑吗
Do you mock me?
阁下的意思是
Sir?
您的儿子
Your son,
叫我把这个带给你
he asked me to bring you this.
没有剑罗伯特怎么保护自己
And how does Robert defend himself if he has no sword?
这浪子永远不会回来了
The prodigal son will not return after all.
没有眼泪  也没有他父亲的原谅
So, no tears, no forgiveness from his father.
做什么都没用了
No amends to be made.
你看到他死的吗
Did you see him die?
他去世的时候我就在旁边
I was with him when he passed.
他念念不忘
His final words were for the l
你们父子之间深深的羁绊
ove and bond between a father and son.
请原谅我的无礼
Forgive my rudeness.
我早就准备迎接这悲伤的一天了
My grief has been waiting for this day.
过来  让我看看你
So come, so that I may see you.
罗宾・朗斯特莱德
Robin Longstride.
一个寻常却高尚的撒克逊名字
A common enough but noble Saxon name.
和我们一起吃晚饭吧
So, you will dine with us.
但是你得先洗个澡  先生
But first, you must bathe, sir.
你太臭了
You stink.
我这儿还有些我丈夫的衣服
I've laid out some of my husband's clothes.
希望你不要嫌弃
I hope you don't find that too discomforting.
尊敬的夫人
My Lady,
我需要有人帮我脱锁子甲
I'll need some help with the chain mail.
威妮弗蕾德
Winifred.
头罩的扣子在我脖颈上
The coif has a clasp at the nape of the neck.
脱下头罩后你就能看到大衣后面的结带
If you take off the coif, you'll find lacings in the back of the tabard.
非常感谢
Thank you.
我帮你把它洗了
I'll have it washed.
马里昂  拿点酒来
Marion, more wine.
你不远万里把剑带给了我
You've taken a long road to bring this to me.
我不知道这是否意味着我该信任你
I cannot decide whether that makes you trustworthy...
亦或是能从你那寻求帮助
or manipulative.
马里昂
Marion,
我不过是在度量我们客人的品质
I'm merely trying to gauge the quality of the man we have as our guest.
他帅吗
Is he handsome?
帅
Yes.
跟没醉酒的农民一样帅
In the way that yeomen sometimes are when they are sober.
先生  说说你的故事吧
Entertain us with a tale of your life, Sir.
我们现在很少有访客了
We don't get many visitors any more.
除了收税的  就是乞丐
Except tax collectors and other beggars.
我不知道我从哪儿来  只知道我去过哪里
I don't know where I'm from. Only know where I've been.
马里昂  他的眼睛是什么颜色的
So, Marion, what colour are his eyes?
我也还不知道
I don't yet know.
年轻人  我有个提议
I have a proposal for you, young man.
你给我带来了这把意义非凡的剑
You brought me this sword, which has great meaning.
如果你能多待一阵子
If you give me your time,
这把剑就送给你了
it is yours.
我可以再留一天  也许更久
I could stay for a day, or more.
我想问个问题
- I have a question to ask you. -
什么问题
And what is your question?
剑柄上的文字是什么意思
The words on the hilt of the sword, what do they mean?
我可以给你讲很多历史
Well, I think I have much to tell you
你的历史
about history, about your history.
谢谢你
That's very kind.
但我的提议还没说完呢
Well, you haven't heard the other half of my proposal yet.
我想让你留在诺丁汉假扮我归来的儿子
I want you to stay in Nottingham and, for the time being,
也就是马里昂的丈夫
become my returned son, and therefore Marion's spouse.
够了
Oh, that's enough!
-你喝太多了  -听着  听着  听着
- You've had too much to drink. - Listen. Listen. Listen.
我们都知道如果你没有丈夫
We both know that without a husband
我死后这土地就不再属于你
you will lose this land when I die.
你能反驳这点吗
Do you dispute that? Hmm?
不能   当然不能  但如果我说他是我儿子
No.
大家都会这么认为  这样你也有了丈夫了
he will be seen as that. And, so as your husband, huh?
这主意不错
It is a fair contract.
我并不是想让你们生孩子或有别的什么
It is not as if I expect you to have children or...
我只是想用剑换你的一点时间  朗斯特莱德
No, the sword for your time, Longstride.
你同意吗
Are you in agreement?
我同意
- Yes. -Marion, go
马里昂  去告诉所有人
tell the staff,
我儿子回来了  我们全家又团聚了
that my son has arrived and our home is now whole again.
让他们敲响教堂的钟来庆祝
Tell them to ring the church bells in celebration.
再多拿点酒来
And more wine, please.
嘿  嘿
Hey! Hey!
清晨我起来的时候
I rose up in the morning.
强烈的渴望总在心口
And I felt a dire need,
让我醉生梦死混过一天再干一杯蜜糖酒
to dream away the dreary day and down a cup of Mead.
那酒能让我感觉到蜜蜂的叮咬
I felt the sting of honeybees.
家酿的啤酒
Home brew.
如果我不是镇上的牧师我绝对想做酒鬼
If I wasn't the village priest, I'd try for the village drunkard.
太迷人了
Oh, great.
男人到了这儿就会变的深情款款
A man could get very affectionate here.
我从没在尼姑庵外面见过女多男少的景象
I haven't seen so many women for so few men outside a nunnery.
泡妞的秘诀就是别去碰最漂亮的那个
The secret to success is never go for the prettiest one.
从左边相貌平平的那个开始吧
Start with the homely one on the left.
那边那个
Right there.
她是我的菜  我要去逗逗她
She's about my size. I'm going to make her smile.
我要去逗你开心
I'm going to make you smile!
过来吧
Come over here!
他们为什么喊你小约翰
So, why do they call you little John?
你想说什么
What are you trying to get at?
我身体很匀称的
I'm proportionate.
多送几桶酒来吧
So roll another barrel to the bar,
再喝他个一两杯让我的心也醉一下
and pour another cup or two so I can soak my heart.
住嘴
Stop it.
我说什么来着
What did I tell you?
看来我们得同住一个房间了
It seems we are to share my chamber.
这样才能让仆人们相信
A ruse to convince the servants.
如果目的是要让他们相信
Well, if the aim is deception,
你难道不该称呼我为"我的丈夫"或者"亲爱的"吗
should you not be addressing me as "my husband,"
开什么玩笑
Don't be ridiculous.
你到底来不来
Well, are you coming or not?
温柔点
Ask me nicely.
请问亲爱的夫君  你愿意跟我共享一室吗
Please, dear husband, will you share my chamber?
你睡这儿
Here.
我带了把匕首睡觉
I sleep with a dagger.
如果你胆敢来碰我  我会不客气的
If you so much as move to touch me,
明白吗
You understand?
谢谢提醒
Thanks for the warning.
狗狗好
Hello, dogs.
戈弗雷
Godfrey.
你的人都到哪儿去了
Where are your men?
他们都死了  大人
They're dead, my Lord.
洛克斯利呢
And Loxley?
还活着
Alive.
那命运把他留给了我来收拾
Then fate has left him to me.
我听到男人的脚步声  早上好儿子
I hear a man's steps. Good morning, my son.
早上好沃尔特
Morning, Walter.
父亲
Father.
你对我的历史都知道些什么
So what is it that you know of my history?
耐心点
Patience.
你今天必须出去示人  带着你的剑
You must show yourself today. Wear your sword.
马里昂
Marion.
我在这儿  沃尔特
I'm here, Walter.
带你丈夫重新熟悉一下他的村庄和村民
Reacquaint your husband with his village and his people.
我去准备马匹
I'll see to the horses.
我感觉自己精神焕发
I feel invigorated.
今早醒来感到一阵蓬勃的生机
I woke this morning with a tumescent glow.
八十四岁了
Eighty-four.
真是奇迹
A miracle.
我一直觉得男人间的谈话很神奇
I've always wondered at the private conversations of men.
丈夫
Husband.
真是个富有的小镇
This is a rich country.
你们的牛羊呢
Where's your cattle and your sheep?
卖了吃了丢了换了  我们已经度过七个荒年了
Sold, eaten, stolen, traded.
现在我们的荤菜是兔子肉
Our meat now is rabbit,
幸运时能打到野猪
or wild pig on a lucky day.
鹿呢
And deer?
如果你愿意冒着被国王砍头的风险的话
If you're willing to risk your neck to the King's executioner.
这土地上每一只鹿都属于他
Every deer in the land belongs to his Majesty.
这些根本不属于国王  它们是上天的恩赐
These things are God's gifts first before the King's possessions.
如果一个人为自己谋生都有罪
If it's illegal for a man to fend for himself,
他怎么争取自己做人的权利呢
how then can he be a man in his own right?
欢迎回家  爵士
Welcome home, Sir.
罗伯特爵士
Sir Robert.
早上好  约瑟夫  艾玛
Good morning, Joseph, Emma.
沃尔特爵士是我们的主人
Sir Walter is our Lord,
你是返乡的罗伯特  你得装的像一点
and you are Robert returned and you should act so.
罗伯特爵士  还记得我吗
Sir Robert. You remember me?
汤姆・张伯伦  养猪的
Tom Chamberlain. Pig farmer.
你看起来一点都没老  汤姆
You don't look a day older, Tom.
罗伯特爵士
Sir Robert.
我们的小伙子们什么时候能回来
When will our young lads come back to us?
能帮我找到我的杰米  让他早点回家吗
Will you find my Jamie, tell him to come home?
没有工作也没有食物  小伙子们都离开了
With no work and little food, the village boys have gone.
去当兵了吗
- To be soldiers?
去偷猎
- Poachers.
看看吧  伙计们
Look at that, mate.
你们还在这儿
Still here then?
现在暂时叫我罗伯特爵士
For the time being, refer to me as Sir Robert. I'l
以后再解释
l explain later.
我亲如手足的兄弟  他们很有礼貌的
My men-at-arms. This is about as courtly as they get.
阿伦・阿德雷  威尔・斯嘉丽还有小约翰
Allan Adayle, Will Scarlet and little John.
马里昂夫人
Lady Marion.
我相信你们昨晚过的很难忘
I trust you had an historic evening.
那是当然
For sure.
马里昂・洛克斯利夫人  我妻子
Lady Marion Loxley, my wife.
真不赖啊
Well played.
尽管有点鲁莽  不过干得不错
A bit rash but well played nonetheless.
真有你的  罗宾
Right you are, Robin.
叫我罗伯特爵士
Sir Robert.
-罗伯特爵士  -爵士
- Sir Robert. - Sir...
-先生  -阁下
- Sir. - Sir.
-呆头爵士  -小萝卜头爵士
- Sir Bob. - Sir Robert.
修道士  你看
Friar.
马里昂  今早从佩珀哈罗传来了好消息
Ah, Marion. Good news travels from Peper Harow this morning.
罗伯特爵士  很高兴再次看见你
Sir Robert, nice to see you again.
你之前就应该明示你的身份
You should've made yourself known when we met i
欢迎你回来
n the field. Welcome home.
是的  请原谅我的冒失  修道士
Yes, I should've. Forgive me, Friar.
这里在干嘛
What happens here?
我们正在把教堂的粮食运往约克
We're moving the church's grain to York.
听说是伦敦新颁布的政策
Politics out of London, I hear.
这是我们大家的种子  它们属于这里的土地
This is our grain. It belongs in this soil.
马里昂夫人  这是上级的意思
Lady Marion, I but follow the orders of my superiors
我不过是服从指令  遵守规定罢了
and abide by their saying and rule.
教皇陛下是否也知道你那些甜美的蜂蜜呢
Does his holiness know about your wealth of honey?
罗伯特爵士  约克的人就是群贪婪的饿狼
There are wolves in York, Sir Robert. voracious wolves.
蜜蜂是我的亲人
The bees are my family.
我不过是个养蜂人
I'm a procreator by design.
并不是什么神职人员  从来都不是
I'm not a churchy Friar. Never was.
蜜蜂赐予了我生的意义
My bees give life.
它们比我的生命还重要  罗伯特爵士
They are my life, Sir Robert.
不应该告诉主教大人吗
Should not the bishop be told
这样圣职人员就能把诺丁汉的蜂蜜涂抹在用诺丁汉的谷物做的面包上了
so the clergy can spread Nottingham honey
倘若这些粮食无法送到约克呢
What if the grain were not to reach York?
那没人会惦记你的蜜蜂
Then the bees need not be spoken of.
认识罗伯特时我已经是个老姑娘了
I was an old maid when Robert courted me.
我母亲是位受人尊敬的寡妇
I was a daughter of a respectable widow
她传承了极少的贵族血统
with a thimbleful of noble blood.
我们结婚了  可仅仅一个星期之后
We were wed, and then a week later
他就跳上了前往法国和圣地的舰船
He left to join ship for France and the Holy Lands.
这就是我的婚姻
And that was my married life to a man
一个陌生的丈夫
I hardly knew.
和一个美好的夜晚[与"骑士"同音]   甜蜜而短暂的夜晚
A good knight.  Short, but sweet.
不  我是说你丈夫是名优秀的骑士
I mean, he was a good knight.
一位身披铠甲的好骑士  战士
A good knight-at-arms, a soldier.
是的  他还是个好男人
Oh, yes, my knight-in-arms, even so.
我们本来应该互相依靠的
And I in his.
住手  你会拧断它脖子的
Stop! You'll break its neck.
马里昂
Marion.
没事的
Easy.
我没事
I'm all right.
我的脚动不了了
I can't move me legs.
谢谢你
Thank you.
亲爱的夫君
My Lord?
现在才轮到我吗
Oh, is it my turn now?
谢谢你
Thank you.
干得漂亮  先生
Nicely done, Sir.
还顺便看见马里昂・洛克斯利夫人的美腿了吧
And to see Lady Marion Loxley's legs,
今天早上之前我以为那是绝对不可能的呢
Beyond my wildest hopes this morning.
我想你应该不认识我的丈夫
I don't believe you know my husband,
罗伯特爵士
Sir Robert.
请容我向你介绍诺丁汉的郡督大人
Allow me to introduce the sheriff of Nottingham.
欢迎回家  罗伯特爵士
Welcome home, Sir Robert.
将国王的公羊救出沼泽
You make your mark quickly
你已经给我们留下了深刻的印象
by rescuing the king's ram from drowning.
你什么意思
What's this?
作为横刀夺爱的回报  我有权向你征收税款
What's mine in coin I have the right
你可以上缴物品或是牲畜
to take in goods or livestock.
倘若这是神的意志
If it's god's will.
这是国库规定一只公羊的税款
Here's a ram's worth of tax for the exchequer.
你对马里昂夫人的无礼
Your insolence to lady marion,
我会给你记上的
I'll consider a debt between us.
来点美味的蜜糖谷醇吗
Mead and grain alcohol?
正合我意
I thought as much.
我们有活要干了
There's something that we need to do.
随时听您差遣
At your service.
好了  伙计们
All right, lads.
早让你们走不走
Should've left while you had the chance.
有活干了  准备下我们就出发
Something's afoot. Off we go.
停下  让马停下
Stop. Stop the horses.
说你呢  靠边点  这可是教会的马车
You there! Move aside! We're on church business!
谁也别想过去
None shall pass
除非猜出这个谜语
unless they can answer the riddle.
他妈的疯子
Moon-mad!
说说看谜语吧  你们这些无礼的混蛋
And what is the riddle, you insolent wretch?
什么东西有18条腿  却哪里也去不了
What has 18 legs and isn't going anywhere?
再敢动一下你就死定了
Your next move will be your last.
晚上好啊  我的朋友
Evening, friend.
告诉我你们是谁
I demand to know who you are.
我们是斗篷人
We are men of the hood.
开心了吧  你自找的
Merry now, at your expense.
假借上帝旨意夺走的...
The Lord taketh...
由我们来归还
and we shall giveth back.
我建议现在就播种  趁着这月光
My advice is to plant it now, by moonlight.
为什么呢  修道士
Why is that, good Friar?
当种子发芽  我就可以说这是上帝的神迹
When it sprouts, I can claim it as a miracle from God.
约克的教会是不会否定神迹的
The church in York would never deny a miracle.
还有多远
- How much further?
大约11英里
- About 11 miles.
我还以为你离开了
I thought you had left.
我们去播种了
The fields have been planted.
我不想吵醒你
I didn't want to wake you.
你怎么找到种子的
How did you find the seed?
我只能告诉你不是天上掉下来的
If you have to ask, it's not a gift.
谢谢你
Thank you.
长枪兵  准备
Pikemen, at the ready!
准备
Arms to ready!
Prepare!
约翰国王可不是我的国王
This King John is no King of mine!
你就是鲍德温吧  我命令你打开大门
You! Are you Baldwin? Open these gates!
你以谁的名义来征伐我
In whose name do you come against us?
约翰国王的命令
In the name of King John.
要么缴税  要么等着被烧死吧
Pay or burn.
查理国王发动战争时我们供奉过金钱和壮丁了
We have paid in money and men for King Richard's wars!
现在已经所剩无几了
And we have no more to give!
-点火  -弓箭手
- Burn it. - Archers!
来啊
Come on.
大人  这边
My Lord, this way!
以约翰国王的名义
In the name of John,
承蒙上帝的恩典  英格兰国王
by the grace of God, King of England,
现在责令强制征税
let it be known to all who abide here that a tax is warranted!
胆敢违抗法令的人
Those persons refusing to abide by the law
将会受到最严厉的惩罚
will hereby be subject to severe punishment.
以上法令奉约翰国王之命
By order of his Majesty, King John.
坦克雷德神父
Father Tancred!
女王陛下
Your Majesty.
我已经对约翰国王失去了信心
I have lost the confidence of King John,
不过我想他还是会听取您的建议
But he may still listen to you.
威廉姆  请不要认为我不懂事理
Allow me to know better, William.
你可比你的猫头鹰要聪明
You are much wiser than your owl.
那是肯定  我比它多活了不少春夏秋冬
I dare say. I've lived longer.
爱德华  把它拿走
Edward, take him.
女王陛下
Your Majesty.
约翰和查理可是天壤之别  女王陛下
John is no Richard, alas, your Majesty.
但我效忠的是会一直延续下去的王权
But I serve the throne, and the throne will endure.
马歇尔  说明白一点  你在担心什么
Speak plainly, Marshal. What's troubling you?
王位已深陷逆境了
The crown is in peril.
戈弗雷与法国国王菲利普串通
Godfrey has been plotting with Philip of France.
法国军队已经在我海岸登陆
French troops have already landed on our shores,
他们以约翰国王的名义大肆杀戮英国人
And they are murdering Englishmen in the name of King John.
北方的贵族将发动内战  颠覆王位
The northern Barons will make civil war against the throne.
这会让我们的海岸线脆弱不堪
Leaving our coast defenceless against the invasion
入侵是迟早的事情
which is certainly coming.
所以  作为约翰的母亲
So it's left to John's mother to scold
我就应该训斥他  提醒他的职责所在吗
him like a child and point him to his duty.
我儿子王宫里面的敌人是他最为亲近的朋友
My son has an enemy in his court closer to him than any friend.
是英国的叛徒  法国人的走狗
An English traitor. A paid agent of France.
为什么你不亲自告诉他  却来找我
Why are you telling me when you must tell the king?
伊莎贝拉
Isabella!
这是你的职责所在
It is you who must do that.
你要告诉约翰国王  你从法国得到消息
Tell King John that you've had word from France, from Philip himself,
甚至可以说是菲利普国王传来的消息
if you like.
为什么不告诉他真相   告诉他威廉姆・马歇尔
Why not tell him the truth?
一个是不被信任的母亲  一个是被他贬职的男人  他会相信吗
Oh! A mother he mistrusts
不会
No.
如果你想做王后  你就必须帮助约翰
If you wish to be queen, you must save John.
还有英格兰
And England.
不
No!
不是真的
No! No!
戈弗雷  这个该死的叛徒
Godfrey! The bloody Judas!
上帝告诉我  你在撒谎
By the bowels of Christ, it's a lie.
你在撒谎
You lie!
亲爱的  对不起
I'm sorry, my love.
-郡督在哪里  -在上面
- Sheriff. - Up there.
有个不愿意透露姓名的人  要求见郡督
Man won't give his name. Demands audience with the Sheriff.
要求
Demands?
退下
- Go away.
遵命  大人
- My Lord.
征税行动迅速
Tax collections proceed apace.
马上就轮到诺丁汉了
Nottingham's turn is coming.
很好  非常好
Good. Good.
请告诉戈弗雷爵士  诺丁汉郡督愿为之效劳
Tell Sir Godfrey that the Sheriff of Nottingham is his man.
这里的一切都听他的安排
May he put his stamp on my authority.
但我想佩珀哈罗的洛克斯利家族会是个麻烦
I see trouble coming from Loxley of Peper Harow.
一个瞎子也会是麻烦吗
A blind old man gives you trouble?
不是他  是他的儿子
Aye, and his son will give more.
十字军战士  罗伯特・洛克斯利   上周刚回来
The crusader, Robert Loxley,
马里昂
Marion.
闪开  闪开
Go on! Go on.
他招供了吗
Has he spoken yet?
他在窥探我们  洛普
He was spying, Loop.
窥探
Spying?
罗伯特  你真丢脸
Robert, I'm ashamed of you.
你好  马里昂
Hello, Marion.
我是来救你的
I've come to save you.
你认识他
Know him?
孩子们  这是罗伯特・洛克斯利爵士  我的丈夫
Boys,
罗伯特爵士  舍伍德森林的逃兵
Sir Robert, the runaways of Sherwood.
放开他
Untie him.
别忙  密探就这样放了不便宜了他
No, I don't think spies should be let off so easily.
这可一点都不友好
That was unkind.
你是十字军战士吗
You were a crusader?
是的
Yes.
都听见了吗  你们抓住了一个十字军战士
Did you hear that, boys? You bested a crusader.
我的人个个都骁勇好战
- My men are good fighters.
我不这么认为
- I don't know about that.
是人多力量大吧
I think the weight of numbers might have been in their favour.
不过他们就如同这森林里的动物  行动起来毫无声息
But they do move silently
这对于人而言是个不错的技巧
But that's only a skill if you stay as a man.
不过别成为你们所猎取的动物
You don't become the creatures you hunt.
我们是战士
- We're soldiers.
不  你们不是
- No, you're not.
战士战而有因  你们又是为了什么
Soldiers fight for a cause. What's yours?
你们没有目标  所以你们只是偷猎者
You don't have one. That makes you poachers.
不过是群小贼  要学的还很多
Common thieves with a lot to learn.
比如呢
Like what?
我可以教你们怎么打结
I could teach you how to tie knots.
我可以教你选用哪种木材能做出最耐用的弓
I could teach you which wood to get to make your bows stronger.
我能教你做可以射出二十多英尺的箭矢
I could teach you how to make arrows that fly more than 20 feet.
我还能帮着马里昂教大家如何保持卫生
And I can help Marion to teach you how to stay clean
这样就不会生病
so you won't get sick.
我不知道你和谁交战  但绝不是我
I don't know who you're fighting, son, but it's not me.
我不是你的敌人
I'm not your enemy.
如果想找人聊天  可以随时来找我
If you want to chat, you know where to find me.
老婆大人  该走了
Wife?
马歇尔
Marshal.
靠边站  为国王让道
Stand aside! Make way for the king!
陛下
Your Majesty.
你在这里搞什么
What the devil are you doing here? Hmm?
陛下
Sire?
你能让那畜生停下来吗  它怎么  瘫痪了吗
Will you keep that animal still? What's it got, palsy?
别以为我还不知道你们想要遗弃我
Do you think I haven't noticed how you've deserted me?
如果陛下还记得  我们最后的谈话
If your Majesty recalls, our last conversation...
我们最后谈话时
At our last conversation,
法国国王菲利普没有派舰队入侵我们
Philip of France wasn't coming our way with an invasion fleet.
对吧  马歇尔
Was he, Marshal?
我朋友戈弗雷
My friend Godfrey
已然不是我记忆中的朋友了
is not the friend I thought he was.
他策划北方贵族反对我
He's stirred up the Northern Barons against me.
他们率军南下
They come south with an army.
马歇尔  他们怎么敢这么做  怎么能
Marshal, how dare they? How dare they?
陛下  被遗忘的人往往是最危险的人
Sire, forgotten men are dangerous men.
你需要告诉北方贵族们
The Barons need to be told
法国人侵略来了  我们要团结起来
that when the French come, we are all Englishmen.
费兹罗伯特
- Fitzrobert.
鲍德温
- Baldwin.
我们会组织一支北方联军  向伦敦进发
We'll make an army of the North and march on London.
军队需要领导者
The Barons need leadership.
睿智的国王知道他们必须真诚对待人民
Wiser kings know they must let men look them in the eye,
认真听取他们的意见
hear their voice.
让我们团结一致  北上与贵族们相接
Together, let us ride north to meet them.
他们在讨伐自己的国王  马歇尔
They march against their King, Marshal.
他们的国王
Their King.
我要让他们看看
We will meet them with the pikes of
我是如何用剑戳穿他们肚子的
our militia in their gizzards.
你已经不识时务了  马歇尔
You have lost your touch, Marshal.
或许北上不应该带你了
Perhaps we'll look to the Barons without you.
把马鞍套上  我要立刻出发
Saddle up with a spare horse. I leave immediately.
我想知道哪里能找到戈弗雷
I want to know where to find Godfrey.
遵命  大人
My lord.
我找到他了  大人
- I found him, my lord.
在哪儿
- Where?
在诺丁汉
Nottingham.
冒充成沃尔特・洛克斯利的儿子大摇大摆
In plain sight, living as Walter Loxley's son.
那我们去诺丁汉
Then we go to Nottingham.
不要俘虏  不留一个活口
Take no prisoners. Leave no stone un-scorched.
带两男四马
Take two men, four horses.
速去海边  然后回巴黎将消息带给国王
Ride hard for the coast, then on to Paris and give a message to the King.
诺丁汉会因我而名留青史
I'll make the place famous.
埃伦  来啊
Come, Allan!
我负责酒水  你负责跳舞
I'll get them drinking. You get them dancing!
太棒了
All right.
音乐  笑声  篝火上棕色的脆皮烤猪
Music, laughter, the crackle of a bonfire and a roasting pig.
幸福又降临了  全得归功于你  罗宾
Life has returned. You have returned it, Robin.
你怎么知道是我
How did you know it was me?
谁会未经请求
Who else would sit by me uninvited
坐在我身边  像个昔日的好友
like a friend from the old days?
威廉姆  你好吗
How are you, William?
还好  就是有点苦恼
I'm well and troubled.
你来这里干什么
Ah. And what brings you?
我今夜将前往巴恩斯代尔
I'm riding on to Barnsdale tonight.
我听说北方贵族
I've heard something of the Barons'
对国王的征税条例满腔愤怒
anger against the crown's tax collector...
怒火已经转化为行动
The anger has turned into action.
他们组织军队准备讨伐国王
They assemble to march against the King.
你觉得你能劝服北方军队回去吗
You think you can persuade the Barons to turn back?
回去  不
Turn back, no.
我会试图说服他们联合约翰国王击退法国侵略者
To join King John
-你说什么  -帮帮我  沃尔特
- A what? - Help me, Walter.
我无法同你前去
I cannot go with you.
我无法认同他
I cannot speak for this King.
可他是我们唯一的国王啊
He is the only King we have.
但并不是我们唯一的希望
But not the only hope.
你什么意思
Explain.
马里昂
- Marion.
我来了  沃尔特
- I'm here, Walter.
这位是我老朋友  威廉姆・马歇尔
This is my old friend, William Marshal.
马里昂・洛克斯利女士  我的儿媳
Lady Marion Loxley, my son's wife.
夫人   很荣幸在罗伯特爵士下船时见了他一面
Lady,
马歇尔  我想你应该清楚
I think you know better, Marshal.
威廉姆爵士   我知道还想再见罗宾・朗斯特莱德一面
Sir William,
我们之前见过
We've met before.
是的  我知道  在伦敦
Yes, Sir, I know. in London.
不  在你很小的时候
No, when you were a child.
还在骑竹马的时候
Hobby-horse age.
沃尔特和我从圣地回来接你回家
Sir Walter and I returned from the Holy Land to fetch you home.
但你已经不在了
But you'd gone.
我们失去了汤姆斯・朗斯特莱德的儿子
We had lost Thomas Longstride's son.
那是永远的痛
It was a wound that never healed.
我需要知道我所知的一切
You need to know what I know.
你父亲是一名石匠
Your father was a stonemason.
你对此满意吗
Is that pleasing to you?
是的
Yes, it is.
但他可不是个普通的石匠  他还是个预言家
But he was more than that. He was a visionary.
他预言了什么
What did he see?
国王需要臣民
That Kings have a need of their subjects,
如同臣民需要国王一样
no less than their subjects have need of Kings.
危险的观点
A dangerous idea.
你的父亲是个哲学家   他有独特的演说方式
Your father was a philosopher.
能够让人心服口服
that took you by the ears and by the heart.
这些东西是不能被写下来的  罗宾
None of these things can be written down, Robin.
你只能将它们铭记于心
You must commit them to your very soul.
这就是记忆的学问
This is the science of memory.
奋起反抗  再反抗  直到羔羊变成雄狮
"Rise and rise again until lambs become lions."
最终  成百上千的人接受了他的观点  也响应了他
Finally, hundreds listened, thousands,
为了所有阶级的权利作斗争的号召
for the rights of all ranks from Baron to serf.
奋起反抗  再反抗
"Rise and rise again,
直到羔羊变成雄狮
until lambs become lions."
他最后怎么了
What happened to him?
闭上眼睛
Close your eyes.
国之根基在于全体人民的自由权利
... foundation is set on the rights of liberty for all people!
朗斯特莱德  交出宪章和他们的名字
Longstride, give up the charter and their names!
你当时在场
You were there.
你亲眼目睹了
You saw it.
不
I will not.
他的精神不能和他一起逝去
Not dead.
至少现在不能
Not now.
这是我摘抄的主要宪章
Here is my copy of the main contract.
这份权利宪章是你父亲所写
This charter of rights was written by your father.
这些是
And here are...
这些是签署宪章的所有贵族的名字
There are the names of all the Barons that signed the charter.
费兹罗伯特  鲍德温  马歇尔  和我
Fitzrobert, Baldwin, Marshal and myself.
他想要的是一部能让所有人
What he wanted was a charter for every man...
在那等着
- Wait there.
享有同等权利的宪章
- to have the same rights.
沃尔特爵士  有信使找您
Sir Walter? A messenger for you.
让他进来
Bring him in.
过来  先生
Step forward, sir.
阁下
- My Lord.
请说吧
- I'm listening.
国王的手下放火烧了彼得伯勒
Peterborough's been burned by the King's men.
费兹罗伯特召集了一队人马
Fitzrobert gathers an army
前往伦敦讨伐约翰国王
to slay King John in London.
马歇尔请您出席在巴恩斯代尔举行的商讨会
Marshal requests your presence at counsel in Barnsdale.
请到外面稍等
Wait outside, will you?
时势造英雄
Cometh the hour, cometh the man.
演戏的时间结束了
The time for pretence is over.
现在  像儿子那样拥抱我吧
Now, hold me like a son.
去吧
Go.
玛吉  夫人在哪
Maggie. Where's my Lady?
我没看到她  阁下
I could not find her, Sir.
无论我们是为活着  为家庭  还是为荣誉而战
Whether we fight for our lives,
我们都必须战斗到最后一刻
we must fight till the death.
威廉姆  你在王宫里待太久了
You've spent too long in the palace, William.
待在王宫里教会了我如何权衡轻重
Spending time in the palace gives me perspective.
就在我们说话的时候
As we speak,
菲利普国王正在乘船前往我们的海岸
King Philip sails for our coast.
戈弗雷 和他的掠夺者都是法国人
Godfrey and his marauders are French!
我们浪费在争议上的每一分钟
Every minute that we waste in disunity
都让国家离毁灭更近一步
brings closer the destruction of our country!
早在戈弗雷之前  我们就已经被
We have been bled
我们的国王弄得遍体鳞伤了
by the king long before Godfrey.
回伦敦去告诉国王
Go back to London and tell the King
决战的地点由他来定
that we will meet him on a field of his choice.
让开
Make way!
我们不会为了保卫约翰的王冠而战
We will not fight to save John's crown.
宁可让他屈服于我们
Rather let him bend the knee to us.
我会给你更多  鲍德温爵士
I'll give you more, Sir Baldwin.
你的剑可以刺入我的胸膛
My breast for your sword point.
你甚至可以用我的剑
Use mine.
来啊
Go on.
不刺吗
No?
这不就是你想要的吗   或许这才是他想要的
Oh, this is what you want, isn't it?
好啊  我宁可把王冠给你  也不愿它被法国人抢走
Fine, I'd rather give it to you
陛下  您误会我了
You mistake me, Sire.
我没有权利  也没有野心戴上王冠
I have no right and no ambition to wear the crown.
但是要让有权戴王冠的人知道
But let the rightful wearer beware.
从今往后  我们只服从于
From now we will be subject only
人民参与制定的法律
to laws that we have a hand in making.
我们不是任你宰割的羔羊
We are not sheep to be made mutton of by your butchers.
戈弗雷策动你们反抗我
Godfrey set himself to turn you against me.
他的真实目的不仅于此
Then he did more than was needed to accomplish that.
一项重要的决定
A very important decision.
大家不认为我们长期以来
Don't you think that we've paid
背负了太多苛捐杂税吗
too much taxes for far too long...
这是我出生的地方
This is where I was born.
这是什么意思
- What does it mean? -
永不放弃
It means never give up.
我们决不会忠于一位残酷剥削人民的国王
We will not be loyal to a crown
国王要听取民意
The king must listen to what we have to say!
国王不会向臣民乞求
A king does not bargain for the loyalty
他们应当给予的忠诚
that every subject owes him.
失去忠诚  国将灭亡  一切都是空谈
Without loyalty there is no kingdom.
我来代表沃尔特・洛克斯利爵士发言
I'm here to speak for sir Walter Loxley.
让他说  让他说
Let the man speak. Let him speak!
说吧
Speak! Speak!
有话就说吧
Speak, if you must.
想要构筑未来
If you're trying to build for the future,
必须夯实基础
you must set your foundation strong.
这片土地的法律  使人民被国王所奴役
The laws of this land
国王要求人民忠诚  却无所回报
a king who demands loyalty but offers nothing in return.
我一路征战  从法国
I have marched from France
到巴勒斯坦  然后归来
to Palestine and back.
我知道
And I know
暴政的结局只有失败
in tyranny lies only failure.
九层之台  起于垒土
You build a country like you build a cathedral,
国家亦是如此
from the ground up.
赋予每个人应有的权利
Empower every man
才能获得支持
...and you will gain strength.
谁能反对这些至理名言
Well, who could object to such reasonable words?
如果陛下愿意给予公平正义
If your Majesty were to offer justice,
以自由权利宪章的形式加以保障
justice in the form of a charter of liberties,
允许人民养家糊口
allowing every man to forage for his hearth,
不被无故定罪
to be safe from conviction without cause
或者无罪入狱
or prison without charge,
人民能够通过自己辛勤劳动谋生
to work, eat and live on the sweat of his own brow
并且尽情享乐
and be as merry as he can...
阁下  戈弗雷的部队正前往诺丁汉
Sir, Godfrey's men are on to Nottingham.
那就能成为一位伟大的国王
...then that King would be great.
不仅能得到臣民的忠诚
Not only would he receive the loyalty of his people,
还能获得人民的爱戴
but their love, as well.
那你有什么建议呢
So what would you have? Hmm?
为每个人建造城堡
Castle for every man?
每个英国人的家就是他们的城堡
Every Englishman's home is his castle.
陛下  我们想要的
What we would ask, your Majesty,
是自由
is liberty.
法律赋予的自由
Liberty by law!
陛下  还有各位大人
Your Majesty, my Lords,
法国舰队到达海峡了
the French fleet is in the channel.
陛下  统一所有国民的机会就在眼前
Sire, you have a chance to unify your subjects high and low.
您点头同意即可
It falls on your nod.
只需要我点头吗
I only have to nod?
我能够做得更好
I can do better than that.
我保证
I give my word,
会制定一部那样的宪章
that such a charter will be written.
我以我母亲的性命起誓
On my mother's life, I swear it.
戈弗雷的军队正向诺丁汉进军   我必须陪伴国王左右
Godfrey makes for Nottingham.
我会派鲍德温  费兹罗伯特和你同去
I will send Baldwin and Fitzrobert with you.
战斗结束后  我们在怀特霍斯会合
We will meet again at the White Horse
罗宾  你父亲是一位伟大的人
Robin, your father was a great man.
虎父无犬子
And you are your father's son.
玛吉  去看看造访我们的是谁
Maggie, who's at the house?
国王万岁
Long live the King!
先生们
Gentlemen.
我是诺丁汉的郡长
I'm the Sheriff of Nottingham.
我的母亲是法国人
I'm French on my mother's side.
沃尔特爵士
Sir Walter! Sir Walter!
洛克斯利
Loxley!
出来
Show yourself!
洛克斯利
Loxley!
谁在这大声喧哗
Who calls here?
我来找罗伯特・洛克斯利
I call for Robert Loxley.
我儿子不在这
My son is not here to answer you.
这倒是真的
That is the truth.
因为他死在法国的壕沟里
Because he's dead in a French ditch.
先生  你是谁  为什么这么说
And who are you, Sir, to say so?
我是谁
Who am I?
我是杀了他的人
I'm the one who killed him.
你有胆的话就和我决斗
Fight me if you dare.
仁慈的主啊
Lord have mercy.
放到桌上  下一个
Leave it on the table. Leave it! Next!
下一个  快点
Next! Come on!
-名字  -洛克斯利
- Name? - Loxley.
教名
Christian name?
马里昂
Marion.
多少土地
Land?
5000英亩
5,000 acres.
马里昂・洛克斯利夫人
Lady Marion Loxley?
是我
I am.
先生们  好好享用吧
Gentlemen, enjoy!
没有人能够拥有4000英亩土地
No one should have 4,000 acres.
5000英亩
5,000 acres.
鲍德温  费兹罗伯特
Baldwin! Fitzrobert!
占领南翼  从西边开始包围
Take the southern flank and circle in from the west.
威尔和埃伦   爬上屋顶  自由射击
Will and Allan,
马里昂夫人
Lady Marion.
快点
Quickly.
跟着我
Follow me.
来人啊  请救救这个孩子
Somebody, please take the baby! Save the baby, please!
约翰  趴下
John, down!
没事了
It's all right.
快散开
Go around.
往后站
Stand back!
让开
Make way!
快点  没事了  请快点
Hurry. It's all right. It's all right. Please, hurry! Hurry!
给我剑
Sword!
趴下  该死的法国狗
Get down, you bastard French dogs!
菲利普国王会在何时何地登陆
Where will King Philip land and when?
这是最后一箭
This is my last arrow.
两天后  在邓杰内斯海湾登陆
Dungeness! Dungeness. Two days.
知道了  我们有两天时间
There we have it. We have two days.
我曾经与一个前往战场的男人告别
Once before I said goodbye to a man going to war.
他却再也没有回来
He never came back.
好好和我告别吧
Ask me nicely.
我爱你  马里昂
I love you, Marion.
朗斯特莱德
Longstride!
沃尔特和诺丁汉那边有什么消息
What news of Walter and Nottingham?
沃尔特爵士过世了  戈弗雷干的
Sir Walter is dead. Godfrey's hand.
先生们  上战场吧
Gentlemen, we go to war.
我第一次征战  由我带队
It is my first time. I shall lead.
前进
Forward!
有很多法国人
That's a lot of French.
接下来怎么做
What's to be done?
弓箭手到崖顶上去
Archers to the cliff top.
骑兵向海滩前进  我们在那等你
Cavalry to the beach. We'll await you there.
跟着我
- With me!
弓箭手
- Archers!
完美的计划
Excellent plan.
骑兵
Cavalry!
准备
Ready!
挽弓搭箭
Raise arrows! Raise arrows!
准备
Ready!
挽弓搭箭
Raise arrows!
放箭
Release! Release!
Release!
上帝啊  马里昂
For the love of God, Marion!
洛克斯利
Loxley,
让你的人马列队  加入进攻
circle your troops and then join the charge.
跟着我
With me!
放箭
Release!
冲啊
Forward!
弓骑兵  前进
Archers, forward!
马歇尔  我们也上
Let's go, Marshal.
陛下  我们靠得够近了
We're close enough, Sire.
对查理来说不够
This was not close enough for Rchard.
那你想想他最后的结局
And look what happened to him.
前进
Forward!
保护国王
Protect the king!
我要为你报仇  沃尔特
This is for you, Walter.
不
No!
马里昂
Marion!
快投降
Surrender!
陛下  陛下
Sire! Sire!
他们投降了  陛下
They've surrendered, Sire!
好啊  向谁投降
Yes! To whom?
他
To him.
朗斯特莱德
Longstride!
我并没有自立为王
I did not make myself King.
那是上帝的旨意
God did.
君授神权
King by divine right.
如今你们拿着这份公文前来
Now you come to me with this document
试图限制上帝赋予我的权利
Seeking to limit the authority given to me by god!
陛下  您曾经起誓了
Sire, you gave your word!
不
No.
陛下  您向我们起誓了
Sire, you give us our word, Sire!
先生  我允许你说话了吗
Did I command you to speak, Sir?
约翰
- John...
或是你  夫人
- Or you, Madam?
陛下  我们将希望寄托于您
Sire, we looked to you!
还是把希望寄托在你们的财产上吧
Look to your estates, instead.
弓箭手
Archers!
你们应该庆幸我现在心怀仁慈
You are fortunate that I am in a merciful mood.
但是对于罗宾・朗斯特莱德   那个石匠的儿子
But as for Robin Longstride,
犯下了偷窃和煽动暴乱的大罪
for the crimes of theft and incitement to cause unrest,
还假冒骑士
who pretended to be a knight of the realm,
其罪当斩
a crime punishable by death,
我宣布  从今往后  剥夺他一切法律权益
I declare him, from this day forth,
一生都将被追捕
To be hunted all the days of his life...
我们不同意
We will not stand for this!
直到他的尸骨腐烂
...until his corpse, unburied, is carrion
成为狐狸和乌鸦的口中餐
for foxes and crows!
听我说
Hear me! Hear me!
国王法令
By royal decree,
罗宾・朗斯特莱德  即罗宾汉
Robin Longstride, also known as Robin of the Hood,
以及任何包庇他  帮助他的人
and all who shelter him or aid him
都会被判为不法之徒
are declared outlaws of the realm,
他们的财产将被没收
their properties forfeit,
任何人发现他们都可以取其性命
and their lives shall be taken by
请给我一个钉子  以及锤子
A nail please? And a hammer.
钉子
A nail!
你可以走了  过来
Off you go. Come on.
孩子们
Hey, boys.
-你们有练习打结吗  -有
- You've been practising tying your knots? - Yes.
有练习射箭吗
Have you been shooting your bow and arrows?
有人射中吗
Who hit something? Anyone?
绿林是无法者的安身之地
The greenwood is the outlaw's friend.
如今  孤儿们欢迎我们的到来
Now, the orphan boys make us welcome.
这里没有苛捐杂税
No tax, no tithe.
没有贫富差距  大自然所给予的一切都被均分
Nobody rich, nobody poor.
国王约翰的统治仍有许多错误需要被纠正
Many wrongs to be righted in the country of King John.
但沃尔特会一直守护着我们
Watch over us, Walter.
为了吾王而战
For the Lion Heart!